<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0">
  <standOff type="recogito_studio_annotations">
    <listAnnotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::47 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::51" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2226">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237BPro"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::96 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::102" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2227">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SAth"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::494 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::505" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2228">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SHAl"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::540 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::546" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2229">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SEle"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::246 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::253" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2230">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380227SSAp"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::490 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::496" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2231">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380227PSik"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::24 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::30" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2232">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380227PSik"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::34 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::40" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2233">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/378226PPhl"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::119 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::125" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2234">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/375224XDeK"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::280 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::289" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2235">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380227SSNy"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::429 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::435" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2236">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/379226PTit"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::94 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::100" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2237">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/383233WAso"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::169 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::178" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2238">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SSem"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::216 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::226" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2239">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SSem"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::52 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::58" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2240">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/378228WAso"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::261 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::267" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2241">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/379226PTit"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::538 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::546" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2242">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/379226PTit"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::587 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::593" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2243">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/379226PTit"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::541 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::551" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2244">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/365379UHie"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::215 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::225" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2245">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/391272PPer"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::314 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::325" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2246">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376231SAsk"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::549 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::555" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2247">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376217UMak"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::56 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::65" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2248">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/379214SCha"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::431 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::440" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2249">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380227BGyS"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::493 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::500" xml:id="UID-FAKE-2250">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOly"/>
      </annotation>
    </listAnnotation>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Book 2, Chapter 11</head>
      <p>Turning away from here towards the gate called Holy you see, not far from the gate, a temple of Athena. Dedicated long ago by Epopeus, it surpassed all its contemporaries in size and splendor. Yet the memory of even this was doomed to perish through lapse of time — the god burned it down by lightning — but the altar there, which escaped injury, remains down to the present day as Epopeus made it. Before the altar a barrow has been raised for Epopeus himself, and near the grave are the gods Apotropaioi (Averters of evil). Near them the Greeks perform such rites as they are wont to do in order to avert misfortunes. They say that the neighboring sanctuary of Artemis and Apollo was also made by Epopeus, and that of Hera after it by Adrastus. I found no images remaining in either. Behind the sanctuary of Hera he built an altar to Pan, and one to Helius (Sun) made of white marble.</p>
      <p>On the way down to the plain is a sanctuary of Demeter, said to have been founded by Plemnaeus as a thank-offering to the goddess for the rearing of his son. A little farther away from the sanctuary of Hera founded by Adrastus is a temple of the Carnean Apollo. Only the pillars are standing in it; you will no longer find there walls or roof, nor yet in that of Hera Prodromia (Pioneer). This temple was founded by Phalces, son of Temenus, who asserted that Hera guided him on the road to Sicyon.</p>
      <p>On the direct road from Sicyon to Phlius, on the left of the road and just about ten stades from it, is a grove called Pyraea, and in it a sanctuary of Demeter Prostasia (protectress) and Kore. Here the men celebrate a festival by themselves, giving up to the women the so-called NymphonYY for the purposes of their festival. In the NymphonYY are images of Dionysus, Demeter, and Kore, with only their faces exposed. The road to Titane is sixty stades long, and too narrow to be used by carriages drawn by a yoke.</p>
      <p>At a distance along it, in my opinion, of twenty stades, to the left on the other side of the Asopus, is a grove of holm oaks and a temple of the goddesses named by the Athenians the Semnai (August ones), and by the Sicyonians the Eumenides (kindly ones). On one day in each year they celebrate a festival to them and offer sheep big with young as a burnt offering, and they are accustomed to use a libation of honey and water, and flowers instead of garlands. They practise similar rites at the altar of the Fates; it is in an open space in the grove.</p>
      <p>On turning back to the road, and having crossed the Asopus again and reached the summit of the hill, you come to the place where the natives say that Titan first dwelt. They add that he was the brother of Helius (Sun), and that after him the place got the name Titane. My own view is that he proved clever at observing the seasons of the year and the times when the sun increases and ripens seeds and fruits, and for this reason was held to be the brother of Helius. Afterwards Alexanor, the son of Machaon, the son of Asclepius, came to Sicyonia and built the sanctuary of Asclepius at Titane.</p>
      <p>The neighbors are chiefly servants of the god, and within the enclosure are old cypress trees. One cannot learn of what wood or metal the image is, nor do they know the name of the maker, though one or two attribute it to Alexanor himself. Of the image can be seen only the face, hands, and feet, for it has about it a tunic of white wool and a cloak. There is a similar image of Health; this, too, one cannot see easily because it is so surrounded with the locks of women, who cut them off and offer them to the goddess, and with strips of Babylonian raiment. With whichever of these a votary here is willing to propitiate heaven, the same instructions have been given to him, to worship this image which they are pleased to call Health.</p>
      <p>There are images also of Alexanor and of Euamerion; to the former they give offerings as to a hero after the setting of the sun; to Euamerion, as being a god, they give burnt sacrifices. If I conjecture aright, the Pergamenes, in accordance with an oracle, call this Euamerion Telesphorus (Accomplisher) while the Epidaurians call him Acesis (Cure). There is also a wooden image of Coronis, but it has no fixed position anywhere in the temple. While to the god are being sacrificed a bull, a lamb, and a pig, they remove Coronis to the sanctuary of Athena and honor her there. The parts of the victims which they offer as a burnt sacrifice, and they are not content with cutting out the thighs, they burn on the ground, except the birds, which they burn on the altar.</p>
      <p>In the gable at the ends are figures of Heracles and of Victories. In the stoa are dedicated images of Dionysus and Hecate, with Aphrodite, the Mother of the gods, and Fortune. These are wooden, but Asclepius, surnamed Gortynian, is of stone. They are unwilling to enter among the sacred serpents through fear, but they place their food before the entrance and take no further trouble. Within the enclosure is a bronze statue of a Sicyonian named Granianus, who won the following victories at Olympia: the pentathlon twice, the foot-race, the double-course foot-race twice, once without and once with the shield.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
