<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0">
  <standOff type="recogito_studio_annotations">
    <listAnnotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::151 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[1]::158" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6503">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOZe"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::147 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::156" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6504">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SANi"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::299 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::305" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6505">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/257326PThe"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::415 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[2]::420" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6506">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/385225SApo"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::556 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[3]::564" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6507">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216BOSt"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::68 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::75" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6508">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/370224UAmy"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::395 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::402" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6509">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/370224UAmy"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::407 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[4]::414" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6510">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOly"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::396 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[5]::402" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6511">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376218GSau"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::246 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::254" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6512">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/433424LCau"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::581 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::589" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6513">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/381241LMaB"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::597 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::609" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6514">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237BSPo"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::613 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[6]::619" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6515">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237BSPo"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::91 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::97" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6516">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/379214SCha"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::120 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::127" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6517">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOZe"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::222 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::227" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6518">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOZe"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::242 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::249" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6519">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOZe"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::357 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::366" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6520">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237AAmz"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::443 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::450" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6521">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237AAmz"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::480 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[7]::489" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6522">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237AAmz"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::94 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::97" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6523">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SOly"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::135 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::145" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6524">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOZe"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::481 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[8]::485" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6525">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOZe"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[9]::42 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[9]::49" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6526">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SOZe"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::139 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::145" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6527">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/371252QLyc"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::243 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::250" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6528">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SAlt"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::336 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::341" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6529">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376216SAlt"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::350 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::358" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6530">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SAkr"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::359 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::368" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6531">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SAkr"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::406 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::415" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6532">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SAth"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::470 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[10]::479" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6533">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/380237SAkr"/>
      </annotation>
      <annotation target="/TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[11]::16 /TEI[1]/text[1]/body[1]/p[11]::25" xml:id="UID-FAKE-6534">
        <rs ana="https://topostext.org/place/376231SAsk"/>
      </annotation>
    </listAnnotation>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Book 5, Chapter 11</head>
      <p>The god sits on a throne, and he is made of gold and ivory. On his head lies a garland which is a copy of olive shoots. In his right hand he carries a Victory, which, like the statue, is of ivory and gold; she wears a ribbon and — on her head — a garland. In the left hand of the god is a scepter, ornamented with every kind of metal, and the bird sitting on the scepter is the eagle. The sandals also of the god are of gold, as is likewise his robe. On the robe are embroidered figures of animals and the flowers of the lily.</p>
      <p>The throne is adorned with gold and with jewels, to say nothing of ebony and ivory. Upon it are painted figures and wrought images. There are four Victories, represented as dancing women, one at each foot of the throne, and two others at the base of each foot. On each of the two front feet are set Theban children ravished by sphinxes, while under the sphinxes Apollo and Artemis are shooting down the children of Niobe.</p>
      <p>Between the feet of the throne are four rods, each one stretching from foot to foot. The rod straight opposite the entrance has on it seven images; how the eighth of them disappeared nobody knows. These must be intended to be copies of obsolete contests, since in the time of Pheidias contests for boys had not yet been introduced. The figure of one binding his own head with a ribbon is said to resemble in appearance Pantarces, a stripling of Elis said to have been the love of Pheidias. Pantarces too won the wrestling-bout for boys at the eighty-sixth Olympiad.</p>
      <p>On the other rods is the band that with Heracles fights against the Amazons. The number of figures in the two parties is twenty-nine, and Theseus too is ranged among the allies of Heracles. The throne is supported not only by the feet, but also by an equal number of pillars standing between the feet. It is impossible to go under the throne, in the way we enter the inner part of the throne at Amyclae. At Olympia there are screens constructed like walls which keep people out.</p>
      <p>Of these screens the part opposite the doors is only covered with dark-blue paint; the other parts show pictures by Panaenus. Among them is Atlas, supporting heaven and earth, by whose side stands Heracles ready to receive the load of Atlas, along with Theseus; Perithous, Hellas, and Salamis carrying in her hand the ornament made for the top of a ship"s bows; then Heracles"exploit against the Nemean lion, the outrage committed by Ajax on Cassandra,</p>
      <p>Hippodameia the daughter of Oenomaus with her mother, and Prometheus still held by his chains, though Heracles has been raised up to him. For among the stories told about Heracles is one that he killed the eagle which tormented Prometheus in the Caucasus, and set free Prometheus himself from his chains. Last in the picture come Penthesileia giving up the ghost and Achilles supporting her; two Hesperides are carrying the apples, the keeping of which, legend says, had been entrusted to them. This Panaenus was a brother of Pheidias; he also painted the picture of the battle of Marathon in the Poikile Stoa at Athens.</p>
      <p>On the uppermost parts of the throne Pheidias has made, above the head of the image, three Graces on one side and three Seasons on the other. These in epic poetry are included among the daughters of Zeus. Homer too in the Iliad says that the Seasons have been entrusted with the sky, just like guards of a king"s court. The footstool of Zeus, called by the Athenians thranion, has golden lions and, in relief, the fight of Theseus against the Amazons, the first brave deed of the Athenians against foreigners.</p>
      <p>On the pedestal supporting the throne and Zeus with all his adornments are works in gold: the Sun mounted on a chariot, Zeus and Hera, Hephaestus, and by his side Grace. Close to her comes Hermes, and close to Hermes Hestia. After Hestia is Eros receiving Aphrodite as she rises from the sea, and Aphrodite is being crowned by Persuasion. There are also reliefs of Apollo with Artemis, of Athena and of Heracles; and near the end of the pedestal Amphitrite and Poseidon, while the Moon is driving what I think is a horse. Some have said that the steed of the goddess is a mule not a horse, and they tell a silly story about the mule.</p>
      <p>I know that the height and breadth of the Olympic Zeus have been measured and recorded; but I shall not praise those who made the measurements, for even their records fall far short of the impression made by a sight of the image. Nay, the god himself according to legend bore witness to the artistic skill of Pheidias. For when the image was quite finished Pheidias prayed the god to show by a sign whether the work was to his liking. Immediately, runs the legend, a thunderbolt fell on that part of the floor where down to the present day the bronze jar stood to cover the place.</p>
      <p>All the floor in front of the image is paved, not with white, but with black tiles. In a circle round the black stone runs a raised rim of Parian marble, to keep in the olive oil that is poured out. For olive oil is beneficial to the image at Olympia, and it is olive oil that keeps the ivory from being harmed by the marshiness of the Altis. On the Athenian Acropolis the ivory of the image they call the Parthenos is benefited, not by olive oil, but by water. For the Acropolis, owing to its great height, is over-dry, so that the image, being made of ivory, needs water or dampness.</p>
      <p>When I asked at Epidaurus why they pour neither water nor olive oil on the image of Asclepius, the attendants at the sanctuary informed me that both the image of the god and the throne were built over a cistern.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
